The following content is
provided under a Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue
to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
So last time
was orthogonal matrices,
Q.
And this time is symmetric matrices, S. So we're
really talking about the best matrices of all.
Well, I'll start
with any square matrix
and about eigenvectors. But you've heard of
eigenvectors more
than once, more than twice,
more than 10 times probably.
So eigenvectors.
And then let's be sure we know why they're
useful.
And maybe compute one or two.
But then
we'll move to symmetric matrices
and what is special about those. And then even more
special and more important will be positive definite
symmetric matrices.
So when I say positive definite,
I mean symmetric. So start with A.
Next comes S.
Then come the special symmetric matrices that
have this extra positive definite property.
So
start with A.
So an eigenvector.
If I multiply A by
x, I get some vector.
And sometimes,
if x is especially chosen well,
Ax comes out in the same direction
as x.
Ax comes out some number
times x.
So normally, there would be for an n by
n matrix. So let's say A is n by n today.
Normally, if we live right,
there will be n different
independent vectors
x eigenvectors
that have this special property.
And
we can compute them by hand if n is 2 or 3,
2 mostly.
But the computation of
the x's and the lambdas. So this
is for
i equal 1 up
to n, if I use this sort of math shorthand,
that I have n of these.
So let's think
about an sometimes what
So that's another n by n matrix.
And we would
ask, suppose we know these guys.
Suppose we found those somehow.
What about a squared?
Is x an
eigenvector of a squared also?
Well, the way to find out is to multiply a
squared by x and see what happens.
Do you see what's going
to happen here? This is a times ax,
which is a times
ax is lambda x.
And now what do I do now?
Because
I'm shooting for the answer yes.
x is an eigenvector of a squared
also.
So what do I do?
That number, that lambda is just a number.
I can put it
anywhere I like. So I can put it out front.
And then I have ax, which
is lambda x. Thanks. So I have another lambda
x. So that's lambda squared x. So I learn
the crucial thing here,
that x is
also an eigenvector of a squared.
And the eigenvalue is
lambda squared.
And of course, I can keep going.
So a to the nth
x is lambda to the nth x.
We have found the right vectors for that
particular matrix A. What about A inverse x?
That will be,
if everything is good,
1 over lambda x.
Well,
yeah.
So any time
I write 1 over lambda, my
mind says,
you've got
to make some comment on the special
case where it doesn't work, which is?
Yeah.
If lambda is not 0,
I'm golden.
If lambda is 0,
it doesn't look good.
But what's happening if
lambda is 0?
A doesn't even have an inverse.
If lambda was 0,
which it could be,
no rule against it.
If lambda was 0, this would say A times
the eigenvector is 0 times the eigenvector.
So that would tell me
that the eigenvector is in the null space.
It would
tell me that the matrix A isn't invertible.
It's taking some vector x to 0.
And so everything clicks.
This works when it should work.
And if we have any function of the matrix, we could
define the exponential of a matrix. 18 .03 would do that.
Let's just
write it down as if we know what it means.
Does it have
the same eigenvector?
Well, sure.
Because e to the at,
the exponential of a matrix,
if I see e to the something,
I think of that long
infinite series that gives the exponential.
All
the terms in that series have powers of A.
So everything is
working. Every term in that series,
x is an eigenvector.
And when I put it all together,
I learn that the eigenvalue is
e to the lambda t.
That's just a typical
and successful use.
OK.
So that's eigenvectors and eigenvalues. And
we'll find some in a minute.
Now,
so I'm claiming that this is the
that from
this first thing, which was just like about
certain vectors are special,
now
we're beginning to see why they're useful.
So special is good.
Useful is even better.
So let me take any vector,
say v.
And OK.
What do I want to do?
I want to use eigenvectors.
This
v is probably not an eigenvector.
But I'm supposing
that I've got n of them.
You and I are agreed that there are some matrices
for which there are not a full set of eigenvectors.
That's really the main sort of annoying
point in the whole subject of linear algebra,
is some matrices don't
have enough eigenvectors.
So almost all do. And let's
go forward assuming our matrix has. OK.
So if I've got n
independent eigenvectors, that's a basis. I
can write any vector v as a combination
of
those eigenvectors.
Right.
And then I can find out
what a to any power.
So that's the point.
This is going to be the simple reason why we
like to have, we like to know the eigenvectors.
Because if I
choose those as my basis vectors,
v is a combination of them.
Now, if I multiply by
a or a squared or a to the k power,
then it's linear.
So I can multiply each one by a to the
k. And what do I get if I multiply that guy
by a to the k -th power?
OK.
Well, I'm just going
to use, or here I said n, but let me say k.
Because n,
I'm sorry, I'm using n for the size of the
matrix.
So I better
use k for the matrix.
The typical
case here.
So what do I get?
Just help
me through this and we're happy.
So what
happens when I multiply that by a to the k?
It's an eigenvector, remember.
So when I multiply
by a to the k, I get?
C1.
That's just a number.
And a to
the k times that eigenvector gives?
Lambda 1. To the
k times the eigenvector.
That's the whole point. And
linearity says, keep going.
Cn lambda n
to the k -th power xn.
In other words, I can apply any power of a matrix. I
can apply the exponential of a matrix. I can do anything
quickly because I've got the eigenvectors.
So really, so I'm saying the first
use for eigenvectors, maybe the principal
use for which they were invented, is
to be able to solve
difference equations.
So if I call that vk,
the k -th power, then
the equation I'm
solving here is?
A one -step difference equation.
This is my difference equation.
And if I wanted to use
exponentials,
the equation I
would be solving would be dv dt equal a v.
Solution to
discrete
steps or continuous time.
Evolution is trivial if
I know the eigenvectors.
Because
here is the
solution to this one.
And the
solution to this one is the same thing. C1
e to the lambda 1 t x1. Is that what
you were expecting for the solution here?
Because if I take the derivative, it brings
down a lambda.
If I multiply by a, it
brings down a lambda.
Plus the other guys.
Not news.
But
important to remember
what eigenvectors
are for in the first place.
Yeah. Let me move ahead. Oh.
One matrix fact
is about something called
similar matrices. So I have on my matrix A.
Then I have the idea of what it means to be
similar to A.
So B
is similar to A.
Or yeah.
What does that mean?
So here's what it
means, first of all. It means that B
can be found from A by,
this is the key operation here,
multiplying by a matrix M and its inverse.
M inverse AM.
When I see
two matrices, B and A,
that are connected by
that
kind of a change,
convertible matrix,
then I would
say B was similar to A.
And
that change,
that
appearance of M is pretty natural.
If I change variables here by M, then I get
that similar matrix will show up.
So what's the key fact? Do you remember the
key fact about similar matrices?
Like that?
They have the same eigenvalues.
So this is
just a useful point to remember.
So this
is like one
fact in
the discussion
of eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
So similar matrices,
same eigenvalues.
Yeah.
So in some
way, in the eigenvalue, eigenvector world,
they're in this,
they belong together.
They are connected by this
relation
that just turns out to be the right thing.
Actually, that gives
us a clue of how
eigenvalues are actually computed.
Well, they're actually
computed by typing eig of A
with parentheses around A.
That's how
they're in real life.
But what happens
when you type eig of A?
Well, you could
say the eigenvalue shows up on the screen.
But something
had to happen in there.
And what happened was
that Matlab or whoever
took that matrix A
started using good choices of M,
better and better,
took a bunch of steps with different M's. Because if I
do another M, I still have a similar matrix, right? If
I take B and do a different M2
to B,
so I get something similar to B, then that's also similar to A. I've
got a whole family of similar things there. And what does Matlab do
with
all these M's, M1 and M2 and M3 and so on?
It
brings the matrix
to a triangular matrix.
It gets
the eigenvalues showing up on the diagonal.
It's just tremendously,
it was an inspiration
when the good
choice of M appeared.
And let me just say,
because I'm going
on to symmetric matrices,
that for symmetric matrices, everything is
sort of clean.
You not only go to a
triangular matrix, you go toward a diagonal
matrix.
You choose M's that make the off -diagonal
stuff smaller and smaller and smaller.
Eigenvalues are not changing.
So they're shooting up
on the diagonal
are the eigenvalues.
So I guess I should verify
that fact, that
similar matrices have the same eigenvalues.
There can't be much
to show. There can't be much in the proof,
because that's all I know.
And I want to know its eigenvalues and
eigenvectors. So let me say, suppose M inverse A M.
Has the eigenvector y
and the eigenvalue lambda.
And I want to show,
do I want to show
that y is an eigenvector also of A itself?
No.
Eigenvectors are changing.
Do I want to show that
lambda is an eigenvalue of A itself?
Yes. That's my point.
So can we see that? Ha.
Can I see that lambda
is an eigenvalue?
There's not a lot to do here.
I mean, if I
can't do it soon, I'm never going to do it.
So what am I
going to do? Define the vector x equals my.
Yeah.
My is
going to be a key. And I can see my coming.
Just
when I see M inverse over there,
what am I going to do with the darn thing?
I'm going to
put it on the other side.
I'm going to multiply that equation by M.
So I'll have,
that will put the M over here. And
I'll have A M y equals lambda M y. Right?
And is that telling me what I want to know?
Yes.
That's saying that M y,
that you wisely suggested to give a name x
to,
is lambda times M y.
You see that?
That the
eigenvalue lambda didn't change.
The eigenvector
did change. It changed
from y to M y. That's the x.
The eigenvector of x.
This is lambda x.
Yeah.
So that's the role of M. It just gives you
a different basis for eigenvectors.
But it does
not change eigenvalues.
Right.
Yeah.
OK.
So those are similar matrices.
Yeah, some other good things happened.
A lot of people don't know. In fact, I
wasn't very
conscious of the fact
that A times B has the same eigenvalues as
B times A.
Well, I should
maybe write that down.
AB
has the same eigenvalues,
the same non -zero ones.
You'll see. I have to, as BA.
This is any
A and B same size. I'm not talking similar
matrices here. I'm talking any two A and B.
Yeah.
So that's a
good thing that happens.
Now,
could we see why?
And then I'm going to be really pretty
happy with basic facts about eigenvalues.
So
if I want to show that
two things have the same eigenvalues, what
do you propose?
Show that they are similar.
I already
said if they're similar. So is there an M?
Is there an M that will connect
this matrix?
So is there an M that
will multiply this matrix
that way?
So that would be similar
to AB. And can I produce BA then?
So I'll just put
the word want up here.
I want.
If I have that,
then I'm done.
Because that's saying that
those two matrices, AB and BA, are similar.
And I know that then they
have the same eigenvalues.
So what should M be?
M should be?
So what is M here?
I want that to be true.
Should M be B?
Yeah. M equal B. Boy.
Not the most hidden fact here.
Take M equal B.
So then I have B times A times B B inverse,
which is the identity. So I have B times A. Yes.
So
AB and BA are fine.
Now,
what
do you think about this question?
Are the eigenvalues? I now know that AB and BA have
the same eigenvalues. And the reason I had to be
careful about
non -zero is that if I
had zero eigenvalues,
then yeah,
I can't count on those inverses.
Right.
So
that's why I put in that little qualifier.
But now I want
to ask this question.
If I know
the eigenvalues of A separately,
by itself, A,
and of B, now I'm talking
about any two matrices, A and B.
If I have two matrices A,
I have a matrix A and
a matrix B,
and I know those are eigenvalues
and they're eigenvalues,
what about AB?
A times B.
Can I multiply the eigenvalues
of A times the eigenvalues of B?
Don't do it.
Right.
Yes.
The eigenvalues of A times the eigenvalues
of B could be damn near anything.
Right. They're not connected
to the eigenvalues of AB. Especially.
And maybe something
could be discovered, but not much.
And similarly for A plus B.
So yeah.
So let me just write down this point. Eigenvalues
of A plus B are generally not eigenvalues
of A plus eigenvalues of B.
Generally not.
There is
no reason. And the reason that I
get that no answer is
that the eigenvectors can be all different. If the eigenvectors for A are
totally different from the eigenvectors for B, then A plus B will have
probably
some other totally different eigenvectors.
And
there's nothing happening there.
Having talked about any matrix A, I'm
going to specialize to symmetric matrices,
see what's special about the eigenvalues there, what's special about
the eigenvectors there. And I think we've already said it in class.
So let me ask
you to tell me again.
So I'll call that matrix S now,
as a reminder always that
I'm talking here about symmetric matrices.
So what are the key facts to
know
eigenvalues? Eigenvalues are real
numbers if the matrix is.
I'm thinking of real symmetric matrices.
Of course, other real
matrices could have imaginary eigenvalues.
Other real matri - so just
let's just think for a moment.
Yeah, maybe I'll just put it here. Can I back
up before I keep going with symmetric matrices?
So take a matrix like that.
Q, yeah, that
would be a Q, but it's not especially a Q.
Maybe the most remarkable thing about that
matrix is that it's anti -symmetric.
So I'll call it A.
Right? If I
transpose that matrix,
what do I get?
Negative.
So that's like anti -symmetric.
And I claim that
an anti -symmetric matrix
has imaginary eigenvalues.
So that's a 90 degree rotation.
And you might say, well, it could be simpler than
that. A 90 degree rotation, that's not a weird matrix.
But from the point of
view of eigenvectors,
something a
little odd has to happen.
Right? Because if I have a 90 degree
rotation, if I take a vector x, any vector x,
could it possibly be an
eigenvector?
Well, apply A to it.
You'd be off
in this direction, AX.
And there is no way
that AX can be a multiple of x.
No real eigenvector for that anti -symmetric
matrix or any anti -symmetric matrix.
Yeah.
So you see that
when we say that the eigenvalues of a symmetric matrix are real, we're
saying that this couldn't happen if A were symmetric. And here, it's the very
opposite. It's anti -symmetric.
Well, while that's
on the board, you might say, wait a minute.
So what is
an eigenvector of that matrix A?
How do you find the eigenvectors
of A?
When they're 2 by 2,
that's
a calculation we know how to do.
You remember the steps
there? I'm looking for AX equal lambda x.
So right now, I'm looking for both lambda and x.
I've got 2 that's not linear. But I'm going to
bring this over to this side and
write it as A minus lambda i x equals 0.
And then I'm going to look at that and say, wow, A minus lambda i must
be not invertible, because it's got this x in its null space. So the
determinant
of this matrix must be 0.
I have a null space unless
the determinant is 0.
And then
when I look at A minus lambda i,
for this A,
I've got minus lambdas
minus A. Oh, A is just a 1.
And that's minus 1.
I'm going to take the determinant. And
what am I going to get for the determinant?
And
I set that to 0.
So I'm just
following all the rules.
But it's showing me that
the lambda,
the 2
lambdas, there are 2 lambdas here.
But they're not real, because
that equation, the roots are i and minus i.
So those are the eigenvalues.
And they
have the nice, they have all the,
well, they are
the eigenvalues, no doubt about it.
With
2 by 2, there are 2 quick checks
that tell you, yeah, you
did the calculation right.
If I add up the 2 eigenvalues,
in this,
if I add up the 2 eigenvalues for any matrix, and I'm
going to do it for this one, I get what answer? Trace.
GILBERT STRANGER. I get the same
answer from the adding, add the lambdas
gives me
the same answer as add the diagonal
of the matrix,
which I'm calling A.
Sum of the eigenvalues,
sum of the lambdas.
Doesn't tell you
each lambda separately,
but it tells you the sum.
So it tells
you one fact by doing one thing.
Yeah.
That's pretty handy.
Gives you a
quick check if you've,
you know, when you compute this determinant
and solve for lambda,
the thing you
do is you, this is
a way to compute eigenvalues by hand.
You could make a mistake, because
it's a quadratic formula for 2 by 2.
But
you can check by adding the two roots,
do you get the same as the trace, 0 plus 0?
Well, there's one other check equally quick for
2 by 2. So 2 by 2s, you really get them right.
What's the other check to,
we add the eigenvalues,
we get the trace.
We multiply the eigenvalues, so we
take,
so
now I'll multiply
the lambdas.
So then I get I times minus I.
And that should equal,
let's don't look yet.
What should it equal? If I multiply the
eigenvalues, I should get the determinant, right,
of A.
So that's two handy checks.
Add the eigenvalues for any size, 3 by 3, 4
by 4. But it's only two checks.
So for
2 by 2, it's kind of, you got it.
3 by 3, 4 by 4, you could still have made an
error, and the two checks could potentially
still work.
Let's just
check it out here. What's I times minus I?
1. Because it's minus I squared, and that's
plus 1. And the determinant of that matrix is
0 minus, is 1. Yeah.
OK. So we got 1.
Good.
Those
are really the key facts about eigenvalues.
But of course,
it's not as
simple as solving AX equal B to find them.
But if you follow through
on this idea of similar matrices
and sort of chop down the off -diagonal part,
then sure enough, the eigenvalues got to show up.
OK.
Symmetric.
GILBERT STRANGER.
Symmetric matrices.
OK.
So now we're
going to have symmetric.
And then we'll have the special, even better
than symmetric, is symmetric positive definite.
OK. Symmetric, you
told me the main facts,
are the eigenvalues real,
the eigenvectors
orthogonal.
And I guess, actually,
yeah.
So I want to put those
into math
symbols instead of words.
So yeah.
Yeah. I guess.
Yeah. Shall I just jump in?
And the other
thing hidden there, but very important, is
there's a full set of
eigenvectors.
Even if some eigenvalues happen to
be repeated, like the identity matrix,
it's still got plenty
of eigenvectors.
So that's an
added point that I've not
made there. And I could prove those two
statements, but why don't I ask you to accept them
and go onward.
What are we
going to do with them?
OK.
And yeah.
Can you just like,
let's have an example.
Just
let me put an example here.
Suppose S, now I'm calling it S,
is 0s, 1s, and 1s.
So that's symmetric.
What are its eigenvalues?
What are
the eigenvalues of that symmetric matrix S?
Plus and minus 1.
Well, if you propose two eigenvalues, I'll
write them down,
1 and minus 1.
And then what will I do to check
them?
Trace and determine it.
OK.
So is it true that
the eigenvalues are 1 and minus 1?
OK.
How do I check the trace? What is the trace
of that matrix?
0.
And what's the sum of
the eigenvalues?
0. Good.
What about determinant?
What's the determinant of S?
Minus 1. The product of the eigenvalues is
minus 1. So we've got it. OK.
What are the eigenvectors?
Minus 1. What vector
can you multiply by and it doesn't change direction? In fact, it doesn't
change at all. I'm looking for the eigenvector that's a steady state.
0, 1. GILBERT
STRANGER. 0, 1? 1, 1.
GILBERT STRANGER. I think it's 1,
1.
Yeah. So here is the lambdas.
And then the eigenvectors are, I think, 1,
1.
Is
that right?
Yeah, sure.
S is just a permutation here.
It's just exchanging the two entries. So 1
and 1 won't change.
And what's
the other eigenvector?
1 and minus 1.
And then
I'm thinking, remembering
about this similar stuff,
I'm thinking that S
is similar to 1.
So S is similar to a matrix that just shows
the eigenvalues.
So
S is similar to, I'm going to put in an M.
Well, I'm going to connect S,
that matrix,
with
the
eigenvalue matrix,
which has the eigenvalues.
So
here is my,
everybody
calls that matrix capital lambda.
Because everybody
calls the eigenvalues little lambda.
So the matrix
that has them is
called capital lambda.
And my claim is that
these guys are similar.
That
this matrix S that you're seeing up there,
I believe there is an M.
So that S, what did I put in here? So I'm following
this pattern. I believe that there would be an M
and an M inverse.
So that this would mean that.
And that's nice.
First of all, it would confirm that the eigenvalues
stay the same, which was certain to happen.
And then it would also mean that I had got a diagonal matrix.
And of course, that's a natural goal, to get a diagonal matrix.
So we might
hope that the M that gets us there is like
an important matrix.
So do you see what I'm doing here? It comes
under the heading of diagonalizing a matrix.
I start with a matrix S.
I find its eigenvalues.
They go on into lambda.
And I believe I can find an M
so that
I see there's similar. They have the same
eigenvalues, 1 and minus 1, both sides.
So only remaining
question is, what's M?
What's the matrix that
diagonalizes S?
What
have we got left to use?
The eigenvectors.
The
matrix that. So can I put the M over there?
Yeah.
That M inverse is going
to go over.
To the other side.
Oh, it goes here, doesn't it? I was worried
there. It didn't look good.
But yeah.
So this is all
going to be right if.
This is
what I'd like to have. S M equal M lambda.
S M equal M lambda.
That's
diagonalizing a matrix.
That's finding the M
using the eigenvectors.
That produces a similar
matrix lambda, which has the eigenvalues.
That's the great
fact about diagonalizing.
That's how you use it. That's another way to say this
is how the eigenvectors pay off. You put them into M.
You take the
similar matrix, and it's nice and diagonal.
So M has the first eigenvector and
the second eigenvector.
And I believe that the
first eigenvector times the second.
And the second eigenvector. That's M again
on this side.
Now let me just write in 1,
0, 0, minus 1.
I see that. How do I do this? So what's the
left side and what's the right side?
So if I multiply
S by a couple of columns,
what's the answer?
Sx1, Sx2. Sx1 and Sx2.
That's the beauty of matrix multiplication.
If I multiply a matrix by another matrix, I
can do it a column at a time.
There are four great ways to
multiply matrices. So this is another one.
A column
at a time. So this left -hand side is Sx1,
Sx2. I just
do each column.
And what about
the right -hand side?
I can do that multiplication.
x1 minus x2, did somebody say?
Death.
No, I don't want.
Oh, x1. Sorry, you said it right.
OK.
When you said x1 minus x2, I was subtracting. But you meant that
the first column is x1 and the second column is minus x2. Correct.
Sorry about that.
And did we come out right?
Yes.
Because now I compare.
Sx1 is lambda 1x1.
Sx2 is lambda 2x2. And
I'm golden.
So what was
the point of this board?
What did we learn?
We learned, well, we kind of expected that
the original S
would be similar to the lambdas
because the eigenvalues match.
S has eigenvalues lambda. And this diagonal
matrix certainly has eigenvalues 1 and minus 1.
A diagonal matrix,
the eigenvalues are right in front of you.
So they're similar. S
is similar to the lambda.
And there should be an M.
And then somebody suggested,
maybe the M is the
eigenvectors. And that's the right answer.
So
finally, let me write that conclusion here,
which isn't just
for symmetric matrices.
So maybe I should put
it for matrix A.
So if it has
lambdas
and eigenvectors,
and the claim is that A
times the eigenvector matrix
is the eigenvector matrix
times the eigenvalues.
And I
would shorten that to A. X equals x lambda.
And I could rewrite that. And then I'll
slow down as A equal x lambda x inverse.
Really, this is bringing it all together in a simple,
small formula. It's telling us that A is similar to lambda.
It's telling us the matrix M that does the
job. It's the matrix of eigenvectors.
And so
it's like a
shorthand way to write
the main facts about eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
What about A squared? Can I go back to the
very first?
I see time is
close to the end here.
What about A squared?
What
are the eigenvectors of A squared?
What are the eigenvalues of A squared?
That's like the whole point of eigenvalues.
Well, or I could just square that stupid
thing. X lambda x inverse x lambda x inverse.
And what have I got?
X inverse x
in the middle is identity.
So I have x
lambda squared x inverse.
And to me, and to you, that says
the eigenvalues have been
squared. The eigenvectors didn't change.
Yeah.
OK. And now
finally, last breath is,
what if the matrix is symmetric?
Then we have different letters.
That's the
only significant change.
The eigenvector matrix is now an orthogonal
matrix.
I'm coming back to the
key facts of what makes symmetric.
What do I see symmetric helping
me in the eigenvector and eigenvalue world?
Well, it tells me
that the eigenvectors
are orthogonal.
So the x is q.
The eigenvalues are real.
And the eigenvectors is
x inverse.
But now I'm going to make those eigenvectors unit vectors. I'm going to
normalize it. So I'm really allowing, I have an orthogonal matrix q. So I
have a different way to write
this. And this is the end of today's class.
q lambda.
And what
can you tell me about q inverse?
It's q transpose.
Thanks. So that
was the last lecture.
So now
the orthogonal lecture is
coming up at the last second of the symmetric matrices
lecture. And this has the name spectral theorem,
which I'll just put this there.
And the
whole point is
that it tells
you what every symmetric matrix looks like.
Orthogonal eigenvectors,
real eigenvalues.